naag.org 2002-06-11

# www.naag.org

## Privacy Policy

Because we gather information about where you go on the National Association of Attorneys General's (NAAG) network of websites and services, we want you to fully understand the terms and conditions surrounding the capture and use of that information. This privacy statement discloses what information we gather, how we use it, and how to correct or change it. 

NAAG collects two types of information about users: data that users provide through optional, voluntary registration for newsletters and other services and aggregated tracking information derived by tallying page views throughout the site. NAAG will not share the information that it gathers about any user, except for some educational contests and legislative activities and then only with the user's express consent, with anyone. The only exception to this general rule is if NAAG must divulge information to comply with state and federal laws and court orders. 

This privacy policy includes a description of the following: 

>   * the information NAAG gathers about you;  
> 
>   * what NAAG does with the information it gathers about you;  
> 
>   * with whom NAAG shares the information it gathers;  
> 
>   * NAAG's opt-in policy;  
> 
>   * NAAG's policy on correcting and updating personally identifiable information; and  
> 
>   * NAAG's policy on deleting or deactivating your name from the site's database.  
> 
> 

Questions regarding this statement should be directed to NAAG at [privacy@naag.org](mailto:privacy@naag.org). 

**1\. Information gathered and tracked by NAAG**

NAAG gathers two types of information about users: (1) data that users provide through optional, voluntary registration for newsletters and other services and for certain public educational activities and (2) aggregated tracking information derived mainly by tallying page views throughout the site and click-through on our newsletters. Such information enables us to better tailor our content to readers' needs. 

NAAG will divulge information about a user to a third-party ONLY with the user's permission and only to complete transactions, e.g., purchases, seminar registrations, and educational contests, initiated by the user (the information to be shared and the parties with whom the information will be shared will be clearly indicated). The only exception to this general rule is if NAAG must divulge information to comply with state and federal laws and court orders. 

NAAG gathers user information in the following processes: 

**Optional Registration:** Several NAAG sites offer free, voluntary registration to users. By registering, users can enter the sites without having to log on each time; they gain access to surveys and polls; and they can take advantage of personalization (i.e., the ability to select content according to a user-supplied profile). 

During registration the user is encouraged to supply a user name, password, and email address and, in some circumstances, has the option to answer other survey questions. In addition, the user can opt to subscribe to various NAAG electronic newsletters and to have his or her email address and/or URL appear in postings. 

**Required Registrations:** For password protected sections, you will be required to provide a user ID and password. To ensure security of the protected sections and the quality of our service you will be required to complete a profile. This ID is encrypted using either authentication from the operating system or by secure socket layer protection. 

**Polling and Surveys:** Several NAAG sites may offer interactive polls to users so they can easily share their opinions with other users and see what the audience thinks about important issues. NAAG uses cookies (see section on cookies below) to "tag" users after they have voted, so they can vote only once on a particular question. This tag is not correlated with information about individual users. 

Some surveys inside the member's only section are used to create detailed demographic information presented in our printed and on-line reports. 

**Message boards/forums:** Users of the NAAG message boards and discussion forums must register separately for these services (both are free of charge) to post messages, although they need not register to visit the site. During registration the user is required to supply a username, password, and email address. 

**Electronic newsletters:** Some NAAG practice areas offer a free electronic newsletter to users. NAAG gathers the email addresses of users who voluntarily subscribe. Users may remove themselves from this mailing list through the subscription management pages. Users can also subscribe to the newsletters at the time of registration. 

NAAG delivers newsletters and other information by e-mail only registered recipients from our subscription center. The management system recognizes the URL that was clicked, and records some information about your computer, such as the browser, operating system, and IP address. 

NAAG also uses the feature of your browser to set a "cookie" on your system. This allows us to measure and report the click through rate on emails delivered and better determine future content. No personally identifiable information is placed in the cookie.

NAAG's "Send this story to a friend" service: A reader can choose to electronically forward a news story to someone else by clicking the link at the top of that story. The user must provide their e-mail address, as well as that of the recipient. This information is used only in the case of transmission errors and, of course, to let the recipient know who sent the story. The information is not used for any other purpose. 

**Surveys:** Occasionally NAAG conducts user surveys to better target our content to our audience. For public surveys we sometimes share the aggregated demographic information in these surveys. We never share any of this information about specific individuals with any third party. 

**Educational Activities:** NAAG may offer from time-to-time educational activities in which we request certain personal information. At a minimum, the required information includes name and email address; in some cases, the user must answer mandatory survey questions about a range of other data. The information gathered in the activity form is used to verify the entrant's identity, to send the entrant an email notification that their entry has been received, and to contact you if follow-up is requested or necessary. There are two situations in which NAAG will divulge this information to a third-party–provided the user gives express consent: 

> •A user may expressly choose to receive additional information from a educational activity partner, in which case the user's personally identifiable information is divulged to the partner;
> 
> •Some of the activities may be hosted on the NAAG site but administered by a partner; in such cases, the information a user provides is passed on to the third party.

Because the rules and terms of each educational activity can vary, information about each activity is clearly posted during the event.

**Usage tracking:** NAAG tracks user traffic patterns throughout all of our sites. This allows NAAG to improve sites on the network by determining ease of use and successful services. Usually we will collect browser type, IP address, and operating system but in certain circumstances may need to collect other data. No personally identifiable information is placed in the cookie.

**Cookies:** A cookie is a small data file that certain Web sites write to your hard drive when you visit them. A cookie file can contain information such as a user ID that the site uses to track the pages you've visited. But the only personal information a cookie can contain is information you supply yourself. A cookie can't read data off your hard disk or read cookie files created by other sites. NAAG uses cookies to track user traffic patterns (as described above), to personalize your experience, to register you for a seminar, and to purchase subscriptions and other publications. 

When you register, NAAG uses a cookie to store a unique, random user ID. We do not store passwords or any personal information about you. We use this ID to identify you anonymously in our database and to track the pages you visit on our site. Cookies also enable you to enter certain NAAG sites without having to log on each time. The user ID is encrypted in the database for added security. 

The "Entrance to Members Only" uses a cookie to verify NAAG members through an ID. We use this ID to identify you anonymously in our database and to track the pages you visit on our site. Cookies also enable you to enter certain NAAG sites without having to log on each time. 

If you've set your browser to warn you before accepting cookies, you will receive the warning message with each cookie. 

You can refuse cookies by turning them off in your browser. You do not need to have cookies turned on to use any NAAG site. However, you do need cookies to participate actively in NAAG's message boards and purchase publications in NAAG's e-commerce store. 

**2\. Use of the information by NAAG**

NAAG uses any information voluntarily given by our users to enhance their experience in our network of sites, whether to provide interactive or personalized elements on the sites or to better prepare future content based on the interests of our users. 

As stated above, NAAG uses information that users voluntarily provide in order to send out electronic newsletters. NAAG never shares newsletter mailing lists with any third parties, including partners. We use tracking information to determine which areas of our sites users like and don't like based on traffic to those areas. NAAG does not track what individual users read, but rather how well each page performs overall. This helps us continue to build a better service for you. 

**3\. Sharing of the information**

NAAG uses the above-described information to tailor our content to suit your needs. We do not share information about individual users with any third-party, except in the case of some educational activities and legislative efforts as noted above and then only with a user's express consent. (NAAG will also divulge information to comply with state and federal laws and court orders.) 

**4\. Opt-in policy**

NAAG will follow an "opt-in" policy. In other words, you will need to sign up to receive newsletters and other information from the NAAG website. Some examples of this policy include: 

> * Opting to receive our electronic newsletters when registering for a site;  
> 
> * Opting to provide certain personal information when registering for a site or when participating in an educational activity (see above); and  
> 
> * Opting to participate in certain interactive areas, which completely alleviates the need to gather any personally identifiable information from our users   
> 

**5\. Correct/update policy**

Users may correct or change the information collected during registration for any site (see above). The instructions for doing this can be found in our personalization area. Users may change this information at any time and as often as necessary. Users who are experiencing problems or who have any questions about how our services work can contact us at [support@naag.org](mailto:privacy@naag.org). 

**6\. Delete/deactivate policy**

Users may unsubscribe to any of our electronic newsletters at any time by following the instructions contained at the end of every newsletter. 

Currently, NAAG does not offer users a means by which to completely delete personal information established at the time of registration for any site.
